If you’re anything like me,
you have lots of ambitious
plans for the future.
I’ve got a whole series of
new books I want to write,
thousands more
videos to script.
But guess what?
None of us may be able to do
any of the things we want to do
if we don't have our health.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
There’s been some alarming news
about colon cancer recently.
Did you know that colon cancer is the
#1 cancer killer among non-smokers?
And that people seem to be
getting it earlier and earlier in life?
Today, we look at the best
diet for a healthier colon.
We have 100 trillion micro-organisms
residing in our gut,
give or take a few trillion, but
“the spread of the Western lifestyle
has been accompanied
by microbial changes,”
which may be contributing to our
epidemics of chronic disease.
The problem is that we’re
eating these meat-sweet diets,
characterized by a high intake
of animal products, sugars,
processed foods, and a low
intake of whole plant foods.
Contrary to the fermentation of
the carbohydrates that make it down
to our colon—the fiber and
resistant starch that benefit us
through the generation of these
magical short chain fatty acids
like butyrate—microbial
protein fermentation,
when excess protein is consumed…
that generates potentially toxic
and pro-carcinogenic metabolites
involved in colorectal cancer.
And so, what we eat
can cause an imbalance
in our gut microbiome and
potentially create a ‘recipe’
for colorectal cancer,
where a high-fat, high-meat,
high processed food diet tips the scale
towards dysbiosis and
colorectal cancer,
whereas a high-fiber and starch,
lower meat diet can pull you back
into symbiosis with your friendly
flora and away from cancer.
We now have evidence from
interventional studies
suggesting that “adopting a plant-based,
minimally processed high-fiber diet
may rapidly reverse the effects of
meat-based diets on
the gut microbiome.”
So, what may be a new form of
personalized microbiome
medicine for chronic disease?
It’s called food, which can
rapidly and reproducibly
alter the human gut microbiome.
Switch people between a whole
food plant-based diet
and more of an animal
food-based diet,
and you can see dramatic
shifts within two days,
which can result in
toxic metabolites.
Switch people to an
animal food-based diet
and levels of deoxycholic
acid go up,
which is a secondary bile
acid known to promote
DNA damage and liver cancers.
Why do levels go up?
Because the bad bacteria
producing the stuff
triple—in just two days.
And over time the richness
of the microbial diversity
in our gut is disappearing.
“A low-fiber diet is a key
driver of microbiome depletion.”
Yeah, there’s antibiotics,
and cesarean sections,
and indoor plumbing,
but the only factor
that has been empirically
demonstrated to be important
is a diet low in MACs
(not Big Macs),
microbiota-accessible carbohydrates,
which is just a fancy name
for fiber found in a whole
plant foods and resistant starch
found mostly in beans, peas,
lentils, and whole grains.
Our intake of dietary fiber,
our intake of whole plant foods,
is negligibly low
in the Western world
when compared to what we evolved
to eat over millions of years.
Such a low-fiber diet provides
insufficient nutrients for
our gut microbes, leading
not only to the loss
of bacterial diversity and richness,
but also to the reduction
in the production
of those beneficial
fermentation end products
that they make with the fiber.
We are in effect, starving
our microbial self.
What are we going to do about
the deleterious consequences
of a diet deficient
in whole plant foods?
Create new-fangled functional foods,
of course, and supplements,
and drugs—prebiotics,
probiotics, synbiotics.
Think how much money
there is to be made!
Or, we could just eat the way
our bodies were meant to eat.
What kind of value is that going
to get your stockholders, though?
Don’t you know probiotic
pills may be the next
big source of big
pharma billions?
Why eat healthy though, when
you can just have someone else
eat healthy for you and
then get a fecal transplant
from a vegan!
Researchers compared the microbiomes
of vegans versus omnivores,
and found the vegan’s friendly
flora were churning out
more of the good stuff,
showing that a plant-based diet
may result in more beneficial
metabolites in the bloodstream
and less of the bad
stuff like TMAO.
But while the impact
of a vegan diet
on what the bacteria
were making was large,
the effect on the composition
of the gut microbiome
was surprisingly modest.
They only found “slight differences
between the gut microbiomes
of omnivores versus vegans”?
That was a shocker to the researchers;
this very modest difference
juxtaposed against
the significantly enhanced
dietary consumption
of fermentable plant foods.
The vegans were eating
nearly twice the fiber.
Anyone see the problem here?
The vegans just barely made the
minimum daily intake of fiber.
Why?
Because Oreos are vegan,
Cocoa Pebbles are vegan,
french fries, Coke, potato chips,
there are vegan Doritos and Pop-Tarts.
You can eat a terrible vegan diet.
Burkitt showed that you need
to get at least 50 grams a day
(of fiber) for colon
cancer prevention.
That’s only half of what our
bodies were designed to get.
We evolved getting
about 100 grams a day.
And that’s what you see
in modern populations
that are immune to
epidemic colorectal cancer.
So, what if instead of
feeding people a vegan diet,
you just fed people
that kind of diet,
a diet centered around
whole plant foods?
We’ll find out next.
Colon cancer is our second
leading cancer killer,
but some places,like rural Africa,
have more than 10 times
lower rates than we do.
The reason we know it’s
not genetic is that
“migrant studies, such as
those in Japanese Hawaiians,
have demonstrated that it
only takes one generation
for the immigrant population
to assume the colon
cancer incidence
of the host Western population.”
Now, the change in
diet is considered
most probably responsible for this.
But there are all
sorts of changes
when you move from
one culture to another—
like smoking rates, different
exposures to chemicals,
infections, antibiotics.
You don’t know if it’s the diet…
until you put it to the test.
This international group of researchers
were trying to find out
why colon cancer rates
were an order of
magnitude higher here—
in African Americans and Caucasians—
than in rural Africa.
Well, if you look at American
colons, they’re a mess:
polyps, diverticulosis—
not to mention hemorrhoids—
whereas the African colons
were remarkably pristine.
And more importantly,
sevenfold lower
colonic epithelial
proliferation rates,
a characteristic of
precancerous conditions.
They measured everything
that they were eating
and concluded that the higher
colorectal cancer risk
and proliferation rates
were most closely
“associated with higher dietary
intakes of animal products”,
which may have led to
“higher colonic populations
of these potentially toxic [acid]
and bile-salt-producing bacteria.”
But you don’t know…
until you put it to the test.
Higher rates are
associated with higher
animal protein and animal fat,
lower fiber consumption,
more of those bad bile acids,
less of those good short chain
fatty acids like butyrate,
and that higher
mucosal proliferation.
But how do we know it’s the
diet that’s mucking things up?
You don’t know…
until you perform an
interventional study.
How about we just
swap their diets?
Feed the Americans a high-
fiber African-style diet,
and those poor Africans get the SAD,
Standard American Diet,
like sausage and white flour
pancakes for breakfast,
a burger and fries for lunch,
and like some meatloaf
and white rice for supper.
That was day one for the rural
Africans in the experiment,
whereas the Americans
were forced to eat
fruits and vegetables,
corn and beans.
To help with compliance they
threw in more familiar foods
like veggie dogs, though
note it was not a vegan diet,
just generally plant-based.
And the food exchanges
weren’t for years,
but just two weeks.
Could they see changes that fast?
The dietary changes
resulted in remarkable
reciprocal changes in the
lining of their colons
in terms of cancer risk
and their microbiome.
Switching to plant-based boosted
the fiber fermentation
and suppressed the carcinogenic
bile acid synthesis.
We know that when our friendly
flora ferment fiber,
they produce beneficial
compounds like butyrate,
which is anti-inflammatory
and anti-cancer.
Well, impressively,
‘Africanization’ of the diet
more than doubled butyrate production,
whereas ‘Westernization’ cut it in half.
In terms of toxic metabolites,
a significant drop on the healthier diet,
whereas the ‘meatloafy’
diet increased the levels
of these carcinogens by 400%
within just two weeks.
So, bottom line (no pun intended):
what they were able to show is
that just by changing the food,
you can remarkably
change your risk.
In fact, that’s how the
lead investigator put it:
“change your diet,
change your cancer risk!”
It may be never too late
to start eating healthier.
Based on these kind of data,
“adopting a whole-food vegan
or [even just] near-vegan diet
rich in fruits and vegetables,”
along with other healthy
lifestyle decisions,
“could have a stunningly
positive impact
on the cancer risks not
only of black Americans,
but of all peoples.”
“While it [might] be
unrealistic to expect
rapid and profound lifestyle changes
in the general population,
[hey]…at least we have
sound, effective advice to offer
to those who [make the choice]
to take the steps needed to
optimize their healthful longevity.”
In our next story,
we look at how modern African diets
may now be as miserably low in fiber
as American diets, but they still
have less cancer than we do.
Colorectal cancer is the
second leading cause
of cancer death in the United
States, after lung cancer.
If you look at the rates of lung
cancer around the world,
they vary by a factor of 10.
If there was nothing we could
do to prevent lung cancer,
if it just rose spontaneously,
happened at random,
you'd assume that the rates
everywhere would be the same,
but since there's such
a huge variation in rates
you assume there's
some external cause,
and indeed we now know
smoking is responsible
for 90% of lung cancer cases.
So if we don't want to die
of the #1 cancer killer,
by just not smoking we can throw
90% of our risk out the window.
For colon cancer there's
an even bigger spread,
bigger variation around the world.
So it appears colon cancer
doesn't just happen,
something makes it happen.
Well, if our lungs can get filled
with carcinogens from smoke,
maybe our colons are getting filled
with carcinogens from food.
Researchers from the
University of Pittsburgh
and the University of Limpopo
sought to answer the question,
'Why do African Americans get more
colon cancer than native Africans?'
Why study Africans?
Because colon cancer is extremely
rare in native African populations,
like more than 50 times lower than
rates of Americans, white or black.
It's the fiber, right?
Dr. Burkitt was the first to describe
the low incidence of colon cancer
in native Africans, ascribing it
to their traditional staple diet
that was high in whole grains
and, therefore, fiber content.
Seems you get about a 10% reduction
in risk for every 10 grams of fiber a day.
So, hey, if it's a 1%
drop for each gram,
and they're eating upwards
of 100 grams a day,
well, that could explain why colon
cancer is so rare in sub-Saharan Africa.
But wait a second, the
modern African diet
is highly processed,
low in fiber,
and yet there has been no dramatic
increase in colon cancer incidence.
The modern African diet
has a low fiber content
as most populations
now depend on
commercially produced
refined cornmeal.
And we're not just talking
low fiber intake,
we're talking United States
of America low,
down around half the
recommended daily allowance.
Yet colon disease still remains rare,
still 50 times less colon cancer.
Maybe it's because they're
thinner and exercise more?
No, they're not,
and no, they don't.
If anything their physical activity
levels may now be even lower.
So if they're sedentary like us,
eating mostly refined carbs,
few whole plant foods,
little fiber -- like us,
why do they still have 50 times
less colon cancer than us?
Well, there is one difference.
The diet of both African Americans
and Caucasian Americans
is rich in meat, whereas
the native Africans' diet
is so low in meat and saturated fat
they have total cholesterol levels
averaging 139, compared
to over 200 in the U.S.
So, yes, they don't get
a lot of fiber anymore,
but they continue to minimize
meat and animal fat consumption
supporting evidence that perhaps
the most powerful determinants
of colon cancer risk are the levels
of meat and animal fat intake.
So why do Americans get more
colon cancer than Africans?
Maybe the rarity of colon cancer
in Africans is not the fiber,
but their low animal
product consumption.
There is a divergence of opinion
as to whether it's the animal fat,
cholesterol, or animal protein
that's most responsible
for the increased cancer risk,
as all three have been shown
to have carcinogenic cancer causing
properties, but it may not really matter
which component is worse, as a diet
rich in one is usually rich in the others.
Finally today,
the fermentation of fiber in the gut may
help explain the dramatic difference
in colorectal cancer incidence
around the world.
More than 30 years ago,
an idea was put forward
that high colonic pH
promoted colorectal cancer.
A high colonic pH may promote the
creation of carcinogens from bile acids,
a process that is inhibited once
you get below a pH of about 6.5.
This is supported
by data like this,
showing those at higher risk for
colon cancer may have a higher stool pH,
and those at lower risk,
a lower pH.
There was a dramatic difference
between the two groups,
with most of the high risk group,
pH over 8,
and most of the low risk group,
pH under 6.
This may help explain
the 50-fold lower rates
of colon cancer in Africa
compared to America.
The bacteria we have in our gut
depends on what we eat.
If we eat lots of fiber then we
preferentially feed the fiber eating bacteria,
which give us back all sorts
of health promoting substances
like short-chain fatty acids
that have anti-inflammatory
and anti-cancer properties.
More of these organic acids
in the stools of native Africans
than African Americans.
More acids, so lower pH.
Whereas putrefactive bacteria
eating animal protein
were able to INCREASE stool pH by
producing alkaline metabolites like ammonia.
The pH of the stools of white versus
lack children in Africa was compared.
Children, because you can more
readily sample their stools,
particularly the rural black school children
who were eating such high fiber diets—
whole grains, legumes, nuts,
vegetables, fruits and wild greens—
9 out of 10 could
produce a stool on demand.
Stuffed from head to tail with plants they
could give you a stool sample at any time,
as easy as getting
a urine sample.
Hard to even get access
to the white kids, though,
who were reluctant to
participate in such investigations,
even though they were given
waxed cartons fitted with lids,
and all the black kids got was
a plate, and a square of paper towel.
What’d they find?
Significantly lower fecal pH in those
eating the traditional rural plant-based diets,
compared to those eating
the western diet,
who were eating far fewer whole
plant foods than the black children.
But remove some of
those whole plant foods,
like switch their corn for
white bread for just a few days,
and their stool pH goes up,
and add whole plant foods like an
extra 5 to 7 servings of fruit every day,
and their stool pH goes
down even further, gets more acidic.
Makes sense, right?
What happens when you ferment plants,
fruits/veggies/grains?
They turn sour, like vinegars,
sauerkraut, sourdough,
because good bacteria like lactobacillus
produce organic acids like lactic acid.
And those who eat a lot of plants have
more of these good bugs in their system.
So using the purple cabbage test,
we want blue pee, but pink poo.
No surprise, then, if you
compare the fecal samples
of those eating vegetarian or vegan,
to those eating standard diets,
plant-based diets appear to shift
the makeup of the bacteria in our gut,
resulting in a significantly
lower stool pH,
and the more plant-based,
the lower the pH dropped.
It’s like a positive
feedback loop.
Fiber-eating bacteria produce
the acids to create the pH
at which fiber-eating
bacteria thrive
while suppressing the group
of less beneficial bugs.
How long does it take to bring
stool pH down on a plant-based diet?
As little as two weeks.
A dozen volunteers carefully
selected for their trustworthiness,
and randomized to sequentially go
on regular, vegetarian, or vegan diet,
and two weeks in, a
significant drop in fecal pH
was achieved eating
completely plant-based.
But there are plant-based diets
and then there are plant-based diets.
Remember these two groups?
Dramatically different stool pH
yet both groups were vegetarian,
but the high risk group was eating
mostly refined grains, very little fiber,
whereas the low risk group was
eating whole grains and beans,
packed with fiber for our fiber-
friendly flora to munch on.
Just as a reduction
of high serum cholesterol
contributes to the avoidance
of coronary heart disease,
so a fall in the fecal pH value may
contribute to the avoidance of bowel cancer,
and through the same means,
eating more whole plant foods.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age” has
been out for about half a year now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.